<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Reyfham in the countie of Norff. the 22. of September, an. Do. 1588 And eftsoones at request published by R.H. minister of Gods worde.</title>
            <author>Humpston, Robert, d. 1606.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03854</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13969</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104324</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840062</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840062</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4533</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03854)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4533)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 549:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Reyfham in the countie of Norff. the 22. of September, an. Do. 1588 And eftsoones at request published by R.H. minister of Gods worde.</title>
                  <author>Humpston, Robert, d. 1606.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wolfe for Edward Aggas,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1589.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Rob. Humston.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4533:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4533:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at Reyfham in the Countie of Norff. the 22. of September, An. Do. 1588. And eftſoones at requeſt publiſhed by R. H. Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of Gods worde.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Eſaiae. 33.15.16. verſes.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>15. He that walketh in Iuſtice, and ſpeaketh righteous things, refuſing gaine of oppreſsion, ſhaking his hands from taking of giftes, ſtopping his eares from hearing of bloud, and ſhifting his eyes from ſeeing of euill.</p>
               <p>16. He ſhall dwell on high, his defence ſhall be the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions of rockes, bread ſhall be giuen him, and his waters ſhall be ſure.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Augustinus in Pſal. 68.</bibl>
               <p>Si tu factus es peccati tui defenſor, Quomodo erit Deus liberator? vt ille ſit liberator tu eſto accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, tu agnoſce vt ille ignoſcat.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON <hi>Printed by Iohn Wolfe for</hi> Edward Aggas. 1589.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4533:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4533:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ To the right reuerend father, EDMVND by Gods good prouidence, <hi>Byshop of Norwich, the dayes of Heaeuen to be</hi> multiplyed with ioyfull increaſe of grace and peace from God the Farher through Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſippus</hi> (my good L.) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing demaunded, why he vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertooke not ſome publique office in the comon wealth. <hi>Si male curarem</hi> (quoth hee) <hi>Dijs diſplicere. Si bene homini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</hi> And thus to auoide the horne of the argument (by ſecrete inſynua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) inferred vpon the premiſſes: that <hi>ſibi vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere</hi> ſhould be his ſuersbie, As the beſt way to eſcape from blame in the world. Whoſe cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in ſome ſorte I could commend, but his concluſion muſt I needes condemne of foule abſurditie. For as there is no man (except he will be invtile <hi>pondus terrae:</hi> and ſuch the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſuffereth not to eate) but holdeth his place as tenant at will by ſpeciall aſsignation and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation from the Lorde, whether it be in the Church or common wealth: So (in trueth) this ſhip willingly admitteth no loyterers, nor that bodie politique, eaſily retaineth corruption, but the one by diſcipline doth exonerate: the other by medicine doth evacuate ſuch noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome burthens as otherwiſe would infect the bodie, or afflict the ſoule.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4533:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The conſideration whereof (in my gheſſe) moued <hi>Plato</hi> to affirme,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſt. 9. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. terent. diuina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. li. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Non ſibi ſoli; ſed patriae, ſe eſſe natum:</hi> and <hi>Cicero</hi> to ſaie, <hi>Neque vllare magis prodeſſe poſsum patriae, quam ſi tradam vias optimarum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um.</hi> In ſemblable perſuaſion Diuines of euerie age haue painfully enlarged their labors, not by inſtance in publique and perticular exerciſe of their function at home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but by writing of Cate chiſmes, penning of Sermons, &amp; putting their ſtudies into print, haue alſo indeuored to profit ſuch abroad (as haplie with all their hearts) would learne, but lack teachers: haue eares to heg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e (and ſoules to ſane) and yet al as want inſtruction. Thus by all poſſible meanes to manireſt their vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt good will to the benefit of the Church, &amp; behoofe of poſteritie. But <hi>ex duro vltima ferro eſt.</hi> For this vnthankfull age of ours, how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly (with playted browes and powting lookes) entertaineth it this ſeruice and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe office, imbracing the while (with heartie applauſe) euerie odde left or bad toye that fond inuention can excogirate. And firſt of all, the enimie of Gods trueth (if rampant) how yelpeth he: <hi>Sicut Cerberus in ſtigio.</hi> If couchant, how hiſſeth he, <hi>Sicut anguis in herba:</hi> and all to confront and ouerbeare each laudable enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe which might further the kingdome of God, or perſuade the trueth of religion among the ſonnes of men.</p>
            <p>Againe, the Atheiſt <hi>(ignauum paecus)</hi> how diſdainfully (with a forked tongue) diſcardeth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4533:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>he each mohument of pietie? how maliciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (in a preiudicat opinion) reiecteth he all cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure that checketh his diſtempered affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s? And who ſo ſhall but croſſe the path of his wicked delightes, <hi>Iam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> faces &amp; ſaxi volant fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror arma miniſtrat.</hi> Moreouer the world affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth a giddie headed crewe <hi>(abſit tamen verho inuidia)</hi> and theſe men of <hi>Arbens,</hi> (forſooth) looke a ſquint at euery occurrante that pat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> not their ſyniſter fiſt. For all beir they ſcorne the dignities of ſchoole, and deride all proro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatine of learning: yet (like Walthams calfe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a peeuiſh choiſe) they will rather <hi>Credere ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini prepter hominem,</hi> than <hi>hominibus propter veritatem:</hi> Who after a while that they haue beard but who me they liſt, and but where they liſt, at length they liſt to heare none at all, but become malcoutent, fall into ſciſme and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, lamentably vexing the Church with all their ſtormes, <hi>En quo diſcordia C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es perduxit miſeros.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet the wealthie Citizens of this world, whome the Apoſtle termeth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>:<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 3.6</note> whoſe Iron ſynowes no labour can bowe, nor lawe binde to the good behauiour.<note place="margin">O <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> oh, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> How ſtand they at defiance with frendlie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profe? how impatiently beare they the lore of reſtraint, induring with delight the bobbes &amp; precious baulmes of ſugred <hi>placentia,</hi> leading them vnwares (as the foole to the ſtockes) to plowe wickednes, to reape in iquitie,<note place="margin">Hoſea. 10.13.</note> and to feede vpon the frime of lyes? But (whome I
<pb facs="tcp:4533:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>warne as brethren,) a laſt ſort ther be alſo, who though in ſinceritie &amp; zeale they wil ſeeme to go before, ſom vn quiet conceit or other (tho) doth ſo trouble &amp; diſtract them, that to ſpeede their fancie, &amp; fixt their pallate were not the leaſt amongſt <hi>Hercules</hi> labours: For one prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher is too formall, another too populer: This mana time ſeruer: that writer a man pleaſer. One Sermon is too full of Doctors &amp; diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, all ſauouring of Arte: another luke-warm or kay-cold, deuoid of all zeale. This brother affecteth a preſent Pulpit man without preme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation: another bringeth boſome ſtuffe, all ſmelling of the Candle, and thus (as he ſaid) <hi>Scinditur innertuns ſtudia in contraria vulgus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uidius.</note> So that thalone view of the face of theſe trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom ſeas (enraged through the iniquitie of the time) doth queſtionles hale away verie manie, otherwiſe, both apt &amp; able to lanche into the deepe, &amp; driveth them back to reſt their boate by the calmer ſhoare, as too too loath to grap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with the multitud <hi>(immanis belua)</hi> to whom profered ſeruice ſeldome commeth in ſeaſon, eſpeciallie in the caſe of controlement.</p>
            <p>But what then? <hi>poſita est ſua meta malignis.</hi> And as one verie well and wiſe lie writeth:<note place="margin">Hieron. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or. li. z. de gloria.</note> 
               <hi>vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus non in populi opinionem ſed in ſeipſam intuetur, nec leges accipit, fed potius imponit ab omni male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum impetu ſemper inuicta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond thoughtes (which experience holdeth the beſt) muſt therefore better aduiſe diuines, eſpecially, and hart the ſeruants of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4533:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>God (to whom that celeſtial Iniunction <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth eſpecially appertaine) manfully to ſtand to their tackle,<note place="margin">Coll. 3.2.</note> &amp; cheerely to hoiſe their ſailes at all aſſaies, ſith neuer befalleth ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke (though manie ſharpe ſtormes) where Chriſt guides the ſterne. And if the world haue moſt vnkindly intreated (nay cruelly perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) the ſonne of God,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.24.</note> ſhall the ſeruant be pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uileged aboue the maſter? And if the ſpouſe her ſelf muſt ſtoope to let the wicked plowe deepe furrowes vpon her back: who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding (as <hi>Hillarie</hi> ſaith) doeth <hi>vincere cum le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditur emergere cum premitur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 129.3. De Trinit. lib. 7.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; exaltari cum hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliatur.</hi> Shall not Gods ſouldiers march on (maugre the malice of men) &amp; proceed with S. Paul by honor &amp; diſhonor,<note place="margin">2. Co. 6.8.</note> by euill report and good report &amp;c. ſith the deareſt Iewels be far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt fetcht: the pureſt mettals haue deepeſt mynes, &amp; <hi>difficilia quae pulchra.</hi> For as cuſtome (though otherwiſe ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the broker of falſhod) hath fitly drawen the Poets verſe into a prouerb of proofe: <hi>Commoditus omnis ſua fert inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>moda ſecum.</hi> Euen ſo aduiſedly &amp; truely ſaid <hi>Diodorus</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Diodorus.</note> And verilie aged is that ſawe &amp; ſeaſoned with long experience: <hi>Quaenocent, docent:</hi> For <hi>ſchola crucis, ſchola lucis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> writing of the conſtancie of Martirs in the grieuous perſecutions of the church:<note place="margin">De Ciuit. dei. li. 22. ca. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Ligabantur, includebantur, caedebantur:</hi> (ſaith he) yea, <hi>trucidabantur, torquebantur, lauie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur.</hi> But (quenching all this crueltie in a word) <hi>Multiplicabantur</hi> (quoth he) <hi>no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pugnantes
<pb facs="tcp:4533:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>pro ſalute, fed ſalutem contemnentes pro ſeruatore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The cauſe ſtanding thus (perdie) the pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grime that will walke to heauenward muſt put on the minde to ouerſtride manie a ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling blocke in the way, and vndertaking his courſe, <hi>nec temere nec timide</hi> muſt heedefullie paſſe the ſtraightes, <hi>per ſaxa, per ignes,</hi> euen through purgatorie it ſelf curragiouſlie main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyning the race from the houre of his firſt breath, vntill the laſt periode of his mortall life. Where (as one ſaieth) <hi>Lachrimae prius nobis deerunt quam cauſa dolendi.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>encea De <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it. bre.</note> And no maruaile at all: for he that wil be crowned muſt not grudg to be croſſed, ſith no conflict no conqueſt, no conqueſt no victorie: nay, the fiercer th'en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter, the more glorious the triumph to him that holdeth out to the end. Otherwiſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with courage and to faile in the courſe, is to looſe the Bravium th'apoſtle propoſeth to the runners. And to fight for a while &amp; faint in the liftes, is to gaine the <hi>opprobrium</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Romanes vpbroyd the Carthagiman Captaine,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cor. 9.24</note> 
               <hi>vincereſcis Hanniball, vti victoria ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcis.</hi> As for me (I aſſure your good L.) I neuer abounded with that humour, nor euer yet la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houred of their diſeaſe whore fingers tickle <hi>Prurigine ſcribendi.</hi> For albeit manie a time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this day I haue beene beſet with requeſt of ſundrie both in profeſſion and vocation of the beſt, yet could I neuer be induced to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nul gate my ſtudies in writing (for cauſes need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les here to repeate) though otherwiſe. (Gods
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4533:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Church be my witnes) I neuer was nice to hide or withhold the dimitalent committed to my truſt, when or whereſoeuer it might doe good. Howbeit, after I had vpon ſpeciall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt preached this ſermon, and was eftſones laboured with aſſiduall entreatie (in zeale of Gods glorie I dare ſaie) to gather and penne the ſame, that (vnworthie tho) it might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come imprinted and imparted with mani. Importunitie (at laſt) ouercame me to condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend and extorted my promiſe to ſet it downe (which as memorie would ſerue I haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely here performed, as the learned of my coate with the other godly auditors of that preſence where it was deliuered I thinke will auerre.) But yet with condition endorſed, that your L. graue cenſure firſt confirming it to the prefle, or commaunding it to ſylence, I would accordingly anſwere expectation with yea or naye. Lo, reuerend father how bluntly this my <hi>Rudis indigesta<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> moles</hi> preſſeth now vpon your charitable patience, whoſe grauitie trial aſſureth mee) is nothing delighted with the emptie ſoundes of hollowe eloquence, but better contented with the frutefull forme of the wholeſome documents: Wherein how ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer my iarrie ſtile go lymping lame and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant, the matter I hope is both profitable and currant. And that ſufficeth me, if the Lord ſhall ſanctifie my ſillie labour to ſome vſe or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, though to ſerue in the vtmoſt courtes of the temple.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4533:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>For the poore widdowes mite, where God is made vmpire ſhall alwayes ouer-ballance the ſuperfluities of that ſort who ſtande vpon their painted ſhea the to drawe a leaden dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger out of an Iverie ſcabberd.<note place="margin">Mar. 12.44. Luk. 21.2.</note> And good fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Latimers</hi> Newe yeares gyft to King Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie the eight (who when other Biſhops ſent rare and riche Iewels of golde and plate, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented a faire newe Teſtament with a Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>karcher wrought about the borders with this inſcription and poeſie: <hi>Fornicatores &amp; adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros iudicabit Deus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eb. 13.4.</note> was (for waight &amp; worth) more valued in Gods accompt, than thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rufling treaſures that abounded in the Court.</p>
            <p>To conclude, if in this my diſcourſe (hether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſubiect to the eare alone, not the ſoundeſt witneſſe among the ſences, but nowe to be ſtript to the eye it ſelfe, the ſubtileſt ſearcher of all the reſt) I haue erred in matter, <hi>humanum eſt errare</hi> (my L.) but my amiſſe once diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the kenne of the learned, <hi>Peccaui</hi> ſhall be my plea: for <hi>hereticum eſſe nolo.</hi> If other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by friuolous digreſſion I haue vndiſcreetly ranged without the ring of my compaſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the man loſt his waie ere he wiſt: for that courſe was farre from my purpoſe, and neuer in my cuſtome, as the beſt acquainted with my faſhion can beſt tell. But if anie thing here in be well or in any meaſure commen dable, let the praiſe he the Lords: the paine the authors: and the profit the Readers, that God which
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4533:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>is all in all, may haue all the glorie. It only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth then that your good L. (according to your wonted curreſie) woulde accept this at my hande, as an infallible pledge of my ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequious minde, and eftſones vouchſafe my feeble pilgrime to take vp his crutch and to wander as a ſtranger in the worlde vnder the couerture of your fauourable protection, that ſo he may finde ſome harbor againſt the ſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die blaſtes and ſcornefull ſpite of malice &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignitie. The God of mercie and all conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion bleſſe your L. in your godlie cares for the Church, and enlarge his graces vpon your heart, chearing vp your aged daies with the gladſome preſence of his bleſſed ſpirit to the aduauncement of his glorie and the auaile of his Zion.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your L. much bounden, &amp; in the Lorde to commaund <hi>Rob. Humſton.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:4533:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Godlie Sermon preached at <hi>Reyfham.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Habakkuk. Cap. 3. verſ. 3.</bibl>
                  <p>God commeth from Teman, and the holie one from mount Paran, <hi>Selah,</hi> His glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie couereth the Heauens, and the earth is full of his praiſe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lord vouchſafing a long and moſt louing viſitation to the people of <hi>Iuda</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> (men and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thron in the Lord beloued) and therein a franke &amp; gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious tender of mercie and ſauing health by the myniſterie of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. Such notwithſtanding was their ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude and ſtubbornes, that no Caueat coulde warne, nor admonition pearſe them, no lenitie could bende, nor ſeueritie breake them. But wretchedly they would enter into oppoſicion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their God, and wilfully runne headlong vpon the pykes of his diſpleaſure: Whereupon he is conſtrained to procéede to execution of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice againſt their rebellion, and to this end (as an inſtrument for the nonce) ſtirreth vp <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bucadneſſer</hi> the great king of <hi>Babell,</hi> who in rage and furie (with his Caldean armie) inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their countrie, moſt lamentably ſacketh &amp;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4533:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſpoileth the land of <hi>Iudea</hi> with fire and ſworde, and marching on with his cruell band towarde the holie Citie, when by length of ſiege he had filled her families with famine and hunger, &amp; her ſtreetes with howling &amp; wringing of hands at the head of euery corner,<note place="margin">Ier. 19.9.</note> at length he razeth her walles, entreth the Citie with a fearefull alarme, fiereth her pallaces, ſpoyleth the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, maketh <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> an heape of ſtones:<note place="margin">2. Re. 25.7.</note> and (after ſundrie preſidents of other fearfull cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties) carrieth away both Prince and people captiues to <hi>Babilon.</hi> All which deſolations (to befall the Church and to ouerwhelme Gods children) our <hi>Habacuk</hi> foreſeeing in the ſpirite of a Prophet (to his no ſmall greefe God wot) and obſeruing withall the flouriſhing eſtate and wiſhed ſucceſſe of the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> (that godleſſe and curſed nation) thus inſulting and trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phing ouer Gods people (a thing to his ſeeming no leſſe wonderfull and ſtrange) in this wofull inſtance of the vnequall lot of the godly and the wicked in this worlde:<note place="margin">Iob. 21.7.</note> the godlye commonly languiſhing in myſerie,<note place="margin">Ier. 12.1.</note> the godleſſe contrarily flouriſhing in felicitie:<note place="margin">Pſa. 73.3.</note> he goeth about to tread the Laberinth, and aſſayeth by reaſon to found the depth of Gods councels in this ſo harde a caſe: But when the helpes of Nature will not reach the height of theſe iudgements, at laſt (as a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an at his wittes ende) he reſolueth to ſtande vpon his watch, to liſten to the Lord alone,<note place="margin">Hab. 2.1.</note> and to heare what he would ſaye to the matter, and eftſones receiuing aunſwere, that howſoeuer
<pb facs="tcp:4533:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>the workes and wayes of God (to the leuell of mans vnderſtanding) ſeeme confuſed and out of ioynt, for his wayes are not our wayes, nor his thoughtes our thoughtes:<note place="margin">Eſai. 55.8.9.</note>) yet for all that, there is no Iudge more iuſt then God, (as <hi>Eſdras</hi> ſaide) nor any more wiſe then the moſt higheſt.<note place="margin">2. Eſd. 7.17.</note> Who ſtandeth not bound to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a reaſon of his proceedings vnto men (for who hath knowen the Lordes minde,<note place="margin">Ro. 11.34.</note> or who hath he made of his counſaile. Our Prophet nowe bluſhing at his former blindnes: brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth out in this Chapter into a Pſalme of praiſe, with earneſt prayer for his ſo great o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſight, and implying the ignorances of the people withall, becommeth an humble ſuter in the Churches behalfe, that (ſith remedileſſe ſhee muſt into <hi>Babylon</hi>) the Lorde woulde not yet ſo forſake her, but when (in depth of griefe and bottome of diſtreſſe) her <hi>De profun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis</hi> and prayer ſhoulde ariſe,<note place="margin">Pſa. 130.</note> and (as the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe) aſcend into his preſence, that then in wrath hee woulde remember mercie, euen for his owne promiſe and names ſake. And groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding altogether vpon grace, he falleth to enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meration and reckoning vp of the marueilous workes brought to paſſe in former time in the behalfe of this Nation. And drawing an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument from the free loue of God in the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull vocation and preſeruation of this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he ſeemeth in great confidence to reaſon with the Lorde, and to frame his demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion after this manner:</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:4533:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>It is vnlike (nay vnpoſſible) O Lorde, that thou (who in mercie haſt numbred the haires of our heades) ſhouldeſt once forgeat or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake that people,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.2.</note> towardes whome thy ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall mercies haue beene ſo often manifeſted of olde.</p>
            <p>But this Nation of the Iewes, is that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for whoſe ſake thou haſt wrought manye and marueylons thinges in tyme paſt:<note place="margin">Num. 21.34.</note> ſtricken manie a fierce battaile: vanquiſht manye a mightie King: Fed with Manna from heauen:<note place="margin">Ioſua. 12.9</note> 
               <note place="margin">Exo. 16.15</note> 
               <note place="margin">Exo. 44.22</note> 
               <note place="margin">Ioſua. 1.</note> Led by wonder through the Sea and brought ſafe to the lande.</p>
            <p>Therefore vnlike, Oh Lorde (nay vnpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) it is that thou ſhouldeſt nowe forget or forſake this people, or ſuffer them to be ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp with ſorrowes in <hi>Babylon.</hi> The Prophet hauing thus handle this argument before, commeth nowe to prooue the <hi>Minor</hi> or latter propoſition by ſounde demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons drawen from the ſeuerall workes, won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully brought to paſſe in fauour of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And (as the worthieſt, and for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie thereof) hee firſte of all propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the giuing of the Lawe in the texte which I haue taken, which may be reduced to this forme.</p>
            <p>That people to whome the Lorde vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) the giuing of the Lawe, with an abſolute abridgement of his owne bleſſed will, ſo preciſely written with his owne hande, and ſo ſolemply promulgate in his owne preſence,
<pb facs="tcp:4533:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>when his glorie couered the heauens, and the earth was full of his praiſe. The ſame doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les is the choſen inheritance and peculier peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God.</p>
            <p>But in fauour of this people of the Iewes, <hi>God commeth from Teman, and the holie one from mount Paran,</hi> where in thunder and wonder the Decalogue &amp; Law of Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments was firſt promulgate and deliuered.</p>
            <p>Therefore doubtles this people is the cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen inheritance and peculier people of God, whom (by conſequent) he will neuer forget nor forſake in their afflictions, ſith in their fauour and for this peoples ſake <hi>God commeth from Teman, and the holie one from mount Paran, &amp;c.</hi> Which wordes (my thought) do imparte a ſecret (but verie ſweete) alluſion vnto <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeach, in affection iumping right, and in phraſe ſomewhat neare with our Prophet, when vpon his death bed, and in his laſt farewell to the people, reisyſing in his ſoule at the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of Gods mercies ſo bountifully extended towards this nation (ayming herein eſpecially at the giuing of the Law) ſaith he <hi>The Lorde came from Smay and roſe vp from Seir vnto them he appeared clearely from mount Paran and came with ten thouſands of Angels,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 33.2.</note> 
               <hi>and a fierie lawe at his right hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where firſt the occaſion of the words (in m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vnderſtanding) offereth two things for our b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in <hi>Habacuk</hi> his example before we come to handle the text it ſelfe.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:4533:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The firſt is his great and tender care for and in the Churches behalfe, expreſſed by his ardent affection in bemoning her calamitie <hi>(onus)</hi> a burthen vpon his heart,<note place="margin">Hab. 1.1.</note> for ſo he beginneth his Propheſie, and withall by his earneſt intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for her reliefe. The ſecond, his confidence relying in Gods free mercie for her deliuerie, manifeſted alſo by his aſſured depending vpon Gods fauour, the verie life of his hope eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed vpon the ſtrength of the couenant. Of both which I would ſpeake ſome what by way of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, but verie briefely, and ſo paſſe to my texte.</p>
            <p>And firſt the Prophets ſweete affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the Church and people of God, a (ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all good part alwayes in a good Paſtor) tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth myniſters of the worde, whatſoeuer they beare, not alone to be inſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon vpon their ſeuerall charge,<note place="margin">2. Ti. 4.2.</note> the flocke purchaſed with the bloud of the Lambe, as men mindfull to auoide the Apoſtles <hi>Vae</hi> and venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance:<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.29.</note> Wo be to me, if I preach not the Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell.<note place="margin">1. Co. 9.16.</note> But withall to bethinke them how it is further required in the Stewards, that they be found faithfull, full of affections, paſtoral care and zeale,<note place="margin">1. Co. 4.2.</note> eſpecially towardes that people and ſtocke committed to their charge,<note place="margin">Ezech. 33.6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> whoſe bloud ſhall be required at their hands. So <hi>Moſes</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred the ſafetie of his people before his owne welfare,<note place="margin">Exo. 32.32.</note> when in heate of ſpirite he cryed vnto the Lorde: Forgiue them or raze me out of the booke of life.<note place="margin">Ier. 9.1</note> So <hi>Ieremie</hi> wiſhed for water to
<pb facs="tcp:4533:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>his heart, and a fountaine of teares to his eyes, that day and night he might wéepe for the ſlaine of the daughters of <hi>Iuda.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ro. 9.3</note> So <hi>Paul</hi> deſired <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natheman eſſe,</hi> and to be ſeparated from God, if thereby he might reconcile the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> his kinſmen after the fleſh. And verily this is the graund charge (fuller of affection than repiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion) which the prince of Paſtors vrged with vehemencie vpon <hi>Peter:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 21.15.</note> Féede, féede, féede. Giuing firſt a dreadfull checke vnto ſuch as ſit at eaſe in <hi>Sion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. 6.1</note> ſleepe in the lappe of the Church, and praye vppon the ſpoyle of ſoules, and couertly implying a needefull Caueat to all preachers of the worde (before their diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie exerciſes) diligently and with due reuerence to put in practiſe all the helpes of reading, ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, meditation, and conference, makinge prayer their keye to open the doore of the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, from prayer to ſtudie, from ſtudie to the Pulpit, from the Pulpit to prayer, and thus by a due reuolution againe to the ſtudie, leſt while by ouerſpeaking wee preſume and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende to auoide the firſt, wee fall vnwares in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to a ſeconde woe, denounced againſt all ſuch as dare take in hande the Lordes worke negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently: and yet when wee haue done what wee can,<note place="margin">Ier. 48.10</note> except God giue winde to our ſayles, wee ſhall neuer runne the poynt aright, but may ſaye with <hi>Peter,</hi> Wee haue laboured all night and taken iuſt nothing.<note place="margin">Luk. 5.5</note> The Lorde make vs more carefull in our calling, and dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble his ſpirite vpon his ſeruauntes, by whoſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4533:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>myniſterie the people are to bee reduced to the obedience of Faith, and increaſe the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of true labourers: for the harueſt is great.<note place="margin">Mat. 9.37</note>
            </p>
            <p>Againe, in the courſe of the Prophet, Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates may alſo learne to whet their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, to become more zealous and truely reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious, carefull to benefite the Church, and to further the courſe of the Goſpell. They may not in imitation of king <hi>Hamon</hi> deface the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 10.</note> nor curtall the liuings of the Clergie, the meſſengers (not of <hi>Dauid</hi>) but of <hi>Dauids</hi> Lorde. They may not ſtretch the arme with <hi>Ieroboam</hi> againſt the Prophet,<note place="margin">I. Re. 13.4</note> nor yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come like <hi>Iulyan</hi> the Apoſtata, as Caterpillers cleauing to the fruites of the Church, but (put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on the bowels of affection and loue) they muſt change their cheare with her happie or hard eſtate, to ſorrow when ſhee mourneth, and to ſing when ſhee reioyceth,<note place="margin">Nehem. 2.3</note> as careful Nouree-fathers and tender Nourſes conſecrated by the Lorde himſelfe to feede his people in <hi>Iacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ro. 12.15.</note> and his inheritance in <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſai. 49.23</note> So good King coulde neuer take reſt, till hee had founde an habitation for the God of <hi>Iacob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 78.71</note> and hauing firſt prepared a place for the Arke,<note place="margin">Pſa. 132 4</note> moſt ioyfully in ſweete conſort of Muſicke daunceth before the ſame.<note place="margin">2. Sa. 6.16 23.</note> Which the nice and ſornful Quéene <hi>Michol</hi> diſdayning, is plagued <hi>perpetua ſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate</hi> to her graue. So <hi>Ioſiah</hi> raigned religiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> carefully, &amp; <hi>Ezechias</hi> zealouſly. <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> graceth <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Emperour with rare commendations, in this eſpecially,
<pb facs="tcp:4533:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>that vpon his death-bed and to his laſt breath, his chiefe care was ſpent for the peace and good eſtate of the Church. Among the worthie ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of King <hi>Edgar</hi> (regiſtred to his renowme) his godly care and good affection towarde the Church is eſpecially obſerued in the ſtorie of his deedes, who hauing reſigned his life &amp; caſt off his Crowne and princely arraye, a learned man of that time (leſt his fame ſhould periſh) clad his bodie with an honorable Epitath, and fit for the herſe of a King, wherein I finde thus much for the preſent purpoſe.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Templa Deo, Templis Monachos, Monachis dedit agros;</l>
               <l>Nequitie lapſum, Iuſticie<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> locum.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Firſt, he was a builder of Churches, but ſo be verie fewe. Secondly, he was a carefull Patrone to implant good miniſters (call them Monkes if ye will) in theſe Churches, but ſo do not manie. Thirdly, he was a liberall ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of landes and poſſeſſions to mainteine theſe miniſters, but ſo do not anie. The Tombs of our time are faire adorned with verſes &amp; flags, &amp; ennobled with Armes and Creſt, but a man may ſeeke all the dayes of his life, and ſearch al the graues of the deade, and yet faile to finde a like preſident of pietie. Well, let all people (of what ſort or ſexe ſoeuer, learne in theſe ſo honorable examples to hallowe their firſte thoughtes, and to dedicate their laſt care, to the Church, and for religions ſake, as eſteeming &amp; ſetting a dearer price vpon heauenly than
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4533:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>earthly, eternall than temporall things. So ſhall all grubbing Patrons of benefices, with their ſacrilegious brokers whatſoeuer, learne at laſt (except they be ſhameles and paſt grace) to reforme their griedie affections (wherin they haue ſwallowed a great parte of the Churches patrimonie) and begin in time to yelde her (at laſt) her owne againe. A thing, in trueth, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be wiſhed than expected. Sith not the <hi>vulgus</hi> alone, but men of greateſt authoritie, &amp; by your leaue, men of great ſinceritie (as they will ſeeme) haue their hande in the ſpoils, and are found guiltie of this treſpas. Wee onely ſtrike the eare with a vaniſhing voyce, it is the Lord that muſt touch the heart with an effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all feeling,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.6</note> elſe we may ſit ſtill hopeles in this behalfe. For, <hi>Cathedram habet in Coelo, qui corda docet in terra:</hi> The heart teacher ſitteth on high.</p>
            <p>Concerning the ſecond obſeruation, to wite, the Prophets confidence &amp;c. True it is,<note place="margin">Pſa. 34.19</note> manie and manifolde be the troubles of the righteous, but the Lord deliuereth ouf of all. Where eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie penitent ſinner may learne by our <hi>Habacuk</hi> in publique or perticuler affliction to take heart of grace in confidence and boldnes: For <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans contraria ſpernit,</hi> and Faith is like the Palme, the more it is preſſed,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the more it ſpr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and ariſeth againſt all temptation. To drawe neare in aſſurance of faith, and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche the mercie ſeat, in the alone merite and mediation of Chriſt the Meſſias, harted on in
<pb facs="tcp:4533:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>the chearefull promiſes of the Goſpel, and that without all doubt or wauering, for he is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that hath promiſed. His will is ſtable, &amp; his gyfts without repentance.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o. 11.29.</note> In which confident aſſurance, the ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Patriarks, the good kings, the holie Prophets and penitent ſinners of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſort, haue always deriued their comfort from this free fauour of God, the onely fountaine &amp; cauſe efficient of all ſaluation. Where learne we firſt to loath and deteſt Pelaganiſme &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Poperie, ſet a broche by the merite-mongers (the enimies of the grace of God) who ſtruggle to erect a <hi>Babell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en. 11.4</note> whoſe top may reach to heauen, and to ſtop the ſtreame of this moſt auncient doctrine, contrarie to all courſe of ſcripture &amp; example of the Saints, who in euery age &amp; occaſion (dealing with God in this caſe) do wholly abandon the mention, &amp; ſmother all thought of merit, a point ſo well knowen (or at leaſt) ſo often taught, that a man would denie it altogether néedeles to ſpeake more expreſſely in this behalfe. The vſe &amp; benefit of this leſſon (we digeſted) wilbe this much.<note place="margin">Luk. 18.11</note> That while our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries dare ſtande vp with the Phareſie to bragge and implead workes in barre before the Iudge, depending (in part) vpon deſert; &amp; buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding (partly) vpon their owne foundation, and therfore ſtil tottering in their doctrine of doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a. 1.6</note> &amp; carried, as the waues of the ſea, one while vp to heauen, &amp; ſuddenly down to hell, as inconſtant in all their wayes. Wee contrarily acknowledge with <hi>Iob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ob. 9.30</note> our vncleannes &amp; with
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4533:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Ieremie</hi> our wickednes,<note place="margin">Ier. 2.22.</note> pitching Chriſt our one and only foundation,<note place="margin">Pſa. 71.16.</note> &amp; with the Pſalmograph making mention of his righteouſnes only <hi>(Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticia omnia exceptione maior)</hi> &amp; made ours by imputation, ſhal ſing care away with the king. Why art thou ſo heauie Oh my ſoule?<note place="margin">Pſa. 42.11</note> truſt in God &amp;c. and ſay with <hi>S. Paul,</hi> therefore iuſtified by faith: We are at peace with God, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord &amp;c. yea, it is God that iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth, and who ſhal condemne. There is now no condemnation to thoſe that be ingraffed into Chriſt &amp;c. In which ſweete confidence, we ſhall attaine the quiet reſt &amp; bleſſed ſecuritie of Gods ſaintes. The knowledge and aſſurance whereof, God for his Chriſtes ſake, daily more and more increaſe confirme and ſeale vp vpon our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences to his euerlaſting glorie and our endleſſe comfort,</p>
            <p>Hetherto of the occaſion. Nowe a worde or twaine of the Phraſe, and ſo to my text.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God commeth from Teman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Blind <hi>Balaam</hi> did ſay, &amp; therefore could ſay:<note place="margin">Nu. 23.19</note> God is not a man that hee ſhoulde repente &amp;c. Where leſt we ſhould fall into the hereſie of the <hi>Anthropomorphitae</hi> we muſt learn that the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the bodie, as to go, to behold, &amp; to come: the paſſions of the mind, as to reioyce, to be gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, to repent &amp; ſuch like, ſo often in holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture aſcribed vnto God, are not ſo to be taken, as though theſe motions &amp; perturbations could fall into the godhead (God forbid) but are to be vnderſtoode in a figure verie apt to helpe
<pb facs="tcp:4533:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>our dulnes, and ſignificant to expreſſe Gods readie mercies alwayes at hande to relieue wretched ſinners: too apt in <hi>Moſes</hi> abſence to fall to Idolatrie,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xo. 32.1.</note> and with the <hi>Bethulians</hi> in the point of perill to preſcribe vnto God.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udith. 7.</note> Therefore becauſe we are fleſh,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en. 6.3</note> and the Lord remembring that we are but duſt,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa. 78.39</note> it pleaſeth him in great mercie to ſtoupe to our infirmitie, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcend to our capacitie, ſpeaking as a man vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mortall men, and to make his mercies pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, afoording vs all the helpes of familiar phraſes of figures, parables, and ſimilitudes in holie writt, together with the Sacraments, ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies and rites of holy Church beſides, thus by all poſſible meanes to eſtabliſh our hearts in aſſurance of his ſauing health: and, by due con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, to conduct vs in the courſe of a holie and Chriſtian life.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, marke I praye, in the Prophets phraſe, the tranſpoſition of the Temple, where ſpeaking of the glorious preſence of God in the Mount at the giuing of the Lawe, which was long and many a day before the time of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie. Neuertheles, he ſetteth it downe here as a thing in <hi>eſſe</hi> and freſh in viewe before their eyes: <hi>God commeth.</hi> Where I take this to be his drift: namely, to aſſertaine this people (right ſhortly to be plunged in diſtreſſe) that God is nowe as neare, and euen comming, to releiue and releaſe them in <hi>Babylon,</hi> as euer in former time,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xo. 19.20.</note> he was a God at hand to their fathers in the mount:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xo. 44.22.</note> at the read ſea: yea, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:4533:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>in time of neede, and therfore he would not haue them daunted nor diſmaide, nor yet to faint vnder the burthen of their afflictions: For <hi>God commeth.</hi> Yea, when the ſpite and rage of the enimie is at the higheſt, and the calamitie and grief of the godly at the heauieſt, then <hi>God</hi> commeth. A noble leſſon, fit for Princes &amp; La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, for rich and poore men, for Maieſtrates, miniſters and euery Chriſtian, ſith no worldly wight (conuerſing in this vale of teares) can purchaſe immunitie from thrall and humane miſerie. Art thou in pouertie, in ſicknes, in ſorrowe, in priſon, in daunger, yea, in death it ſelfe, <hi>God commeth,</hi> at whoſe preſence, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe departeth, and dread ſhall flye backe: For he is a God almightie, no power can let him: a God all mercifull, no ſtay can preuent him. He commeth ſkipping ouer the mountaines,<note place="margin">Cant. 2.8.</note> &amp; ryding vpon the wings of the winde:<note place="margin">Gen. 3.8</note> To <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> with the promiſe in time of diſpaire:<note place="margin">Gen. 22.11</note> To <hi>Abraham</hi> with ſupplye in time of ſacrifice:<note place="margin">Gen. 26.3.</note> To <hi>Iſaack</hi> with reliefe in time of famine:<note place="margin">Gen. 39.2.</note> in time of exile with honor to <hi>Ioſeph:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Re. 19.8</note> in time of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, with comfort to <hi>Eliah:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iud 1.7.0</note> in time of bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile, with a hand in <hi>Gedeons</hi> hilt:<note place="margin">2. Re. 19.6.</note> and in time of inuaſion, with triumph to <hi>Ezechia:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 6.22</note> to-<hi>Daniell</hi> among the Lions:<note place="margin">Suſan. 60</note> to the children in the fornace: to <hi>Suſanna</hi> at the ſtake:<note place="margin">Act. 16.26</note> to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtle in the gaole:<note place="margin">Luk. 23.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> to the theefe vpon the croſſe in the moment of death: yea, the bandes of death ſhall breake, and the paines of hell ſhall leaue holde: for <hi>Veniens, veniet.</hi> He ſhall come at a
<pb facs="tcp:4533:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>pinch. His wrath endureth but the twinckling of an eye: beauines may laſt for a night, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy for an houre, but ioye commeth in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Oh therefore, whatſoeuer be thy caſe or condition, tarrie patiently the Lordes leaſure, and he ſhall make the ende happie:<note place="margin">Pſa. 27.16.</note> For <hi>God commeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſhort but verie ſweete leſſon, and ſweeter than the Lute to driue dumps from the heart, and to abandon in wealth wickednes, in health wantonnes, in mirth forgetfulnes, in want di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſtfulnes, in loſſe penſiuenes, and in death fearfulnes.</p>
            <p>Againe, <hi>God commeth.</hi> Howe dare then theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> proceede in their cruelties? How dare bloudie <hi>Antiochus</hi> afflict the Church? how dare cruel <hi>Iezabel</hi> murther the Prophets how dare prowd <hi>Sennacherib</hi> blaſpheme the lining God?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Re. 19.2.</note> how dare wicked <hi>Herode</hi> behead <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt? how dare churliſh <hi>Diues</hi> deſpiſe the wofull <hi>Lazarus?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 16.19.</note> and how dare the wicked world ſet it ſelf againſt God? For he commeth. &amp; where wilt thou hide thyſelfe? If thou clyme vp to heauen, euen there he wil find thée. If thou go downe to hell,<note place="margin">Amos. 9.2.</note> his power wil preuent thée. If thou make a way with the wings of the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, his preſence onertakes thée. If thou woul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſmoother ſinne in the bottome of thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, there is a worme to gnaw and grind thée. If thou call vpon the hilles to fall vpon thée, or crye to the mountaines to hide and coner thée, it will be in vaine, it cannot preuail thée: for <hi>God
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4533:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>commeth,</hi> a conſuming fire, a terrible Iudge, a fierce reuenger. And now ſhal the wicked find it as true as terrible,<note place="margin">Deut. 4.24.</note> that it is a fearefull thing to fal into the hands of the liuing God. Oh conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this, ye that forget God, leſt he take you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in your wickednes: for if his wrath be kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled but a little, Bleſſed are all they that put their truſt in him. And thus at laſt I come to the Text: which for order and memories ſake, I wil diſpoſe to the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of the ſimple: Wherein, obſerue with me (I pray) theſe foure circumſtaunces naturallye ariſing out of the words.</p>
            <p>The firſt, of the perſon: Who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth? <hi>God.</hi> The ſecond, of the place: from whence? <hi>From Teman, &amp; mount Paran.</hi> The thirde, of the manner how: in glory? <hi>For his glorie couereth the Heauens.</hi> The fourth &amp; laſt, the end, and why he commeth? <hi>That the earth may be ful of his praiſe.</hi> Who commeth: Whence, How, and why he commeth.</p>
            <p>Concerning the firſt, (to wit, of the perſon) I minde not to propound <hi>Hiero</hi> his queſtion to <hi>Simonides:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cicer. de nat. deoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> For Chriſtians haue alreadie lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; that touching the incomprehenſible maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and eſſence of the great and eternall God, Mans knowledge is too ſhallowe to compro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hende the vnmeaſurable depth. of this hidden myſterie. When Reaſon therefore woulde be ouerbolde and buſie in this ſcutanie: let Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ouer-rule her: for where reaſon leaueth, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beginneth: that religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> propoundeth, faith
<pb facs="tcp:4533:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>apprehendeth: that faith aſſureth, hope hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth: and that hope enioyeth, Loue ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh. But the <hi>interim:</hi> who ſo ſhall ſauce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie prie with the <hi>Bethſhamites</hi> into the Arke ſhall aſſuredly finde deſtruction,<note place="margin">1. Sa. 6.19</note> and he that wil curiouſly gaze vpon the maieſtie of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, ſhall be oppreſſed with the glorie thereof. A leſſon to be looked vnto &amp; in time to be lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the ſecreat Arrians of our dayes, whoſe proude and inſolent ſpirites cannot be conteined within the limits of this religious compaſſe, till wayward conceit haue carried them head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into damnable hereſies. Wherof we haue dailie examples.<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Leand.</note> It was a graue ſpeach of <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie,</hi> that the ſacred Scriptures are like a déep foord, where the Lambe may yet ſafely wade, when the Elephant ſhall ſwimme. And right well ſaide <hi>Auguſtine: Humilitas omnia que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque benefacimus &amp; precedat &amp; comitetur &amp; conſequatur.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt. 56.</note> Humilitie is the entrance, the middle and ende of all that is well done. And thus we may be warned, not ouerbuſilie to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue this point of the Eſſence and maieſtie of God.</p>
            <p>A ſecond and ſafer way to better our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and benefit our ſelues in this behalfe, is by the names of God, whereby it pleaſeth him to manifeſt (in ſome ſort) his exiſtence, all ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciencie and mairſtie, as when he ſaith to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham:</hi> I am <hi>Schad dai,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 17.1</note> all ſufficient to vpholde and ſuſtains the creatures in heauen and earth, at whoſe almeſbaket both King and Kayſar are
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4533:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>brinen to begg their daily bread: at whoſe hand the eyes of all creatures do expect their foode in due time, and at whoſe mercie ſeate all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde muſt knocke and crye for grace and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſinnes.</p>
            <p>To <hi>Moſes,</hi> I am <hi>Iehouah,</hi> the eſſentiall name of God,<note place="margin">Exo. 3.6</note> to ſhewe (as mans capacitie may beare it) his eſſence and being of himſelfe before all eternitie, from whome all things haue their breath, mouing and being. Againe, he is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time called <hi>Theos</hi> of his ſwiftnes and preſence,<note place="margin">Act. 17.24</note> paſſing through the ſecrete corners &amp; priuie pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the heart, &amp; vnderſtanding our thoughts long before. Sometime, the Lorde of Hoſtes,<note place="margin">Pſa. 46.8 11.</note> to expreſſe his almightines, with Frogges and Flyes ſubduing Kings, and conquering Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons at his own will. Here he is called <hi>Elohah</hi> and the holy one, all verie ſweete and ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant to ſet foorth the power of God, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the feare of his moſt holie name. Where wee muſt be warefull leſt wee become ſotted with Popiſh ſuperſtitions, or inchanted with Romiſh ſorceries, as though the wearing or bearing about vs theſe names of God, written in virgin parchement, with croſſes and carac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were of force to cure maladies, to chaſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way bugges and caſt out diuels, which in truth is blaſphemouſly to abuſe and take in vaine the holie name of God to our owne deſtruction. But learne we rather to harbour and carrie the power &amp; faith of this name deepe in our hearts: So ſhall it be to our comforts and victorie in al
<pb facs="tcp:4533:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>temptation: For this is our victorie that ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth Sathan, ſinne, &amp; the worlde, euen our faith.<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.4</note> A third and verie good way to help yet in this caſe, is by conſideration of the offices attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to the perſons in the Godhead: as Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Father, and therein his wonderfull wiſedome, diſpoſing and tranſpoſing all things to his owne will: in the frame of wheſe proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, all the actions and accidents among the ſonnes of men are daily wrought, and come to their appointed end. Redemption to the ſonne, and therein his inſpeakable mercie towardes mankinde, moſt willingly affording the dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt droppes of his heart bloud for the raunſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of wretched ſinners. Sanctification to the Holy ghoſt, and herein the ineruaylous and powerfull hand of our God, in changing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing the hearts of men, raiſing vs daily from the death of ſinne vnto the life of righteouſnes.</p>
            <p>Uerye comfortable be theſe alſo to expreſſe and manifeſt the great care and goodnes of our God,<note place="margin">Pſa. 86.15</note> by nature mercifull, long ſuffering, ſlowe to wrath, and readye to pardon wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. It is his mercye to take awaye the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and wayght of our ſinnes, but it is his great mercie to renue vs with indumentes of grace in this life, and to crowne vs with glorye in the life to come. And hitherto of the firſt cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance.</p>
            <p>And now to the ſecond, to wit, of the place. <hi>From Teman and from mount Paran.</hi> Where, whether you take <hi>Taeman</hi> for that Citie of <hi>Idu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maea</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:4533:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>buylded by <hi>Teman</hi> one of the Tukes of the ſonnes of <hi>Eſau,</hi> and threatened by <hi>Ieremie</hi> with vtter extirpation,<note place="margin">Gen. 36.1</note> becauſe the <hi>Edomites</hi> or <hi>Idumaeans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Icr. 49.20</note> and namely the inhabitantes of <hi>Taeman</hi> did ſollicite and ſurge the <hi>Babylonians</hi> to warre againſt the <hi>Iewes,</hi> who therefore praye againſt them: <hi>Remember the children of Edom, O Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 137.9</note> 
               <hi>in the daie of Ieruſalem &amp;c.</hi> Or elſe, as ſpoken by waye of alluſion to the lande of <hi>Canaan,</hi> which in reſpect of mount <hi>Sinay</hi> lay South: For ſo <hi>Tremaellius</hi> tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it, and others from the Hebrewe phraſe, do ſeeme to inſinuate. And as touching <hi>Paran,</hi> whether you take it as it is deſcribed for a waſt and large Wildernes extended from <hi>Egypt</hi> vnto mount <hi>Sinay</hi> and ſo towarde <hi>Canaan,</hi> ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther elſe properly for a promontorie and hill in this deſert, taking denomination of the ſame and adiacent vnto <hi>Sinay</hi> where the Lawe was giuen, which by the text and the place of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> cited before ſeemeth moſte probable. Or whether you will thus interprete it: <hi>God E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lohah,</hi> commeth from <hi>Taeman</hi> with a reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging hande, hauing inkindled a fire in <hi>Teman</hi> which ſhall deuoure the Pallaces of <hi>Boſrha,</hi> and God <hi>Sanctus</hi> commeth from mount <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran</hi> with a releeuing and holye hande to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a holye Lawe, and to a holye people. <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cti eſtote, quoniam ſanctus ſum:</hi> For holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe beſt becommeth his houſe and people for euer. Howe ſo euer (I ſaye) you liſt to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande it. (For I liſt not to bee curious in
<pb facs="tcp:4533:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſcanning of places, or deſcribing their ſcitua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.) This I take to be the Prophets mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: namely, to extoll the tender mercies of the Lord ſo mightily deliuering, and ſo merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully releeuing his people in their ſo long and tedious iourneys through the deſart, where hee fedd them from heauen, watred them from the rockes, bare them in his armes as a father doth his ſonne: carried them on Egles wings moſt ſwiftly and ſafely from all perill and daunger, and that which more is, and moſt excellent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue al, vouchſafing them in this place the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calogue and Lawe of Commaundements to be their wiſedome, direction and ſanctification e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen all the dayes of their life. And here of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe I will paſſe by the matter and manner of Gods mercies in the deliuerance of this people. For why ſhould I inſiſt vpon the point, which is the verie ground of my ſong, and foundation of all my building this daye, and will take oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion rather to ſpeake ſomewhat of the place of Gods preſence to his people, of the place of his worſhip: of preaching, hearing, praying, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating, of adminiſtration of Sacraments, and participation of the rites of holie Church. Where firſt of all I muſt freely confeſſe (and moſt true it is) that euery Chriſtian hath a Temple within him. Euerie Temple hath an Altar. Euerie Altar hath a Sacrifice. Euerie place in dedicate to Gods ſeruice. Euerie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeuer is a Prieſt to offer, and for euery ſort of men lifting vp pure hands without wrath and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4533:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>contention. This is the doctrine of the Holye ghoſt ſcattered throughout Gods booke, &amp; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in bleſſed be God, we are farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Donatiſme,</hi> and tying of the worſhip of God to place or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. And yet for all that, the holye aſſemblies &amp; congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Chriſtians to preaching, praier and publique celebracion of the ſeruice of God, and that in the Temple ſacred and dedicated to this vſe, is a thing by ſo often repetition co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and commended of God himſelfe in holye Scripture, as his own ordinance,<note place="margin">Leuit. 3.3.</note> that it may be vrged by an argument, <hi>a neceſſitate mandati,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioel. 1.14.</note> euen vpon our allegeance. <hi>Eſaie</hi> ſpeaking of the Temple &amp; the vſe thereof in the perſon of God,<note place="margin">Eſai. 56.7</note> I will bring them (ſaith he) to my holye moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and I will make them glad in my houſe of prayer, their burnt offerings will I there ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, and it ſhall be called the houſe of prayer for all men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ezechiels</hi> oracle fitteth vs alſo in this raſe:<note place="margin">Eze. 43.7</note> where (ſpeaking of the preſence of Gods grace: not for the Temple, but for the peoples ſake) he calleth it the place of Gods throne, and the place of the ſoales of his feete, where he will dwell in the middeſt of his people. And <hi>Michea</hi> calleth <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> the tower of the flocke, where the watchman of <hi>Iſrael</hi> doeth warde and garde his folke moſt ſafely from day to day:<note place="margin">Mich. 4.8</note> So that this point might againe be inforced by an argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>a praemils.</hi> But what ſhoulde I ſpeake of the ſweete varietie and riche plentie of thoſe plants and flowers in this heauenly Paradize <hi>(odor
<pb facs="tcp:4533:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>vitae ad vitam)</hi> watered by the dewe of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, flowing with ſtreames of comfort to the wounded conſcience,<note place="margin">Co. 2.16</note> by meanes of the worte and Sacramentes, where the prayers of the Congregation are compared by an auncient fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Murmuri maris</hi> to the violence and noyes of the Seas, that pearce the eares of <hi>Iehouah,</hi> and with force burſt into his preſence (euer-bearing all impedimentes? Why ſhoulde I ſtraine my voice to excite and ſtirre you vp to <hi>the religious and diligent frequenting of theſe</hi> heli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> aſſemblies, where Chriſt hath promiſed hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> preſence to two or three gathered in his name. Whither you are daily tolled to holy ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of pietie and deuocion for the better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of your knowledge and growing vp in the feare and nurture of the Lorde.<note place="margin">Mat. 18.20</note> When in this caſe anye ſhall be ſilent, and men waxe mute, let the Sermon bell ſounde ſhame to the ſluggar be with a woe to the crue of worldlings that wallowe vppon their beddes of Iuorie, make cheare in bowles,<note place="margin">Amos 6.4</note> and ſpende their dayes in vanitie, retchleſly neglecting the tyme of their viſitation.</p>
            <p>And heere I doe reiect the franticke and ſciſmaticall opinions of the Anabaptiſticall ſeet commonly called Browniſſes, who haue wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully deuided and rent themſelues from oure congregations: denye vs to haue any Church: contempne our Sacramentes, and condemne our Religion as Antichriſtian. The <hi>interim</hi> betaking themſelues to priuate meetings, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4533:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſeerete conuenticles in corners. Oh how farre be theſe vermines from King <hi>Dauids</hi> ſpirit and ioye. One thing haue I deſired,<note place="margin">Pſa. 17.4</note> and that (ſaith he) I will require, euen that I may dwell in the Lordes houſe all the dayes of my life, to beholde the beautie of the Lorde, and to viſite his Temple. Againe, <hi>Leratus ſum in his,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 12<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It did him good at his heart, when they ſaide: Let vs goe into the houſe of the Lorde: yea, and againe: <hi>Quam dilecta &amp;c.</hi> Oh howe ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able are thy dwellings thou Lorde of hoſtes:<note place="margin">Pſa. 84.12</note> my ſoule hath a longing thereunto.</p>
            <p>O howe farre he theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> from <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Emperour his ſpirite and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, who (being excommunicate for his of, fence at the great mutanie in <hi>Theſſalia</hi> by <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Millayne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">An. Dom. 391</note> and ſo by the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches cenſure, cut off from the Communion of the faithfull) ceaſeth not in brackiſh teares to bewayle his wretched eſtate, and daye by daye to daunce attendance in humilitie and peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencie to craue reſtitution, till at laſt he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine receiued into the Church. But if ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ioyes of a king can induce them in time to retire, nor an Emperours ſorrowes yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to come hume by weeping croſſe,<note place="margin">21 Sam 12 13</note> with open &amp; humble acknowledgement of their offence to returne with <hi>Dauid</hi> in time,<note place="margin">Mat. 27.4</note> leſt <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das Peccaui</hi> come too late: Then let the Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate (by whoſe negligence this ſect mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrouſly ſwelleth with daylye increaſe in diners parts of the land) Haue an eye this waye, leſt
<pb facs="tcp:4533:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>fooliſh pittie, ſpoyle a citie, and peſter a comon wealth with a people full of blaſphemies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and not all void of treaſons againſt the King. <hi>Dioniſius</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> for bare not to tell <hi>Nouatus</hi> to his teeth, that the ſinne is greater to breake the vnitie and peare of the Church,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ſeb. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ta Conſt.</note> than to commit Idolatrie. And reaſoning <hi>a paena</hi> in the example of <hi>Chore,</hi> that quoth he was puniſhed with the ſworde, but this with the yawning of the earth. <hi>Et non du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitatur ſcaeleratius eſſe commiſſum quod gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius erat vindicatum.</hi> That, ſaith hee, was more haynouſly committed, which was more heauily puniſhed.</p>
            <p>And now to the thirde circumſtance, namely the manner of Gods comming in theſe wordes: <hi>His glorie couereth the Heauens.</hi> Which as you ſee are diſcerned from the former parte of the texte,<note place="margin">Pſa. 3.2.4.8</note> by this worde <hi>Selah</hi> full oft obſerued in the booke of Pſalmes,<note place="margin">Pſa. 4.2.4</note> and ſeruing in the old Church for the ſingers direction in the change of their voyce or tune.<note place="margin">Pſa. 9.16.20</note> But here,<note place="margin">Pſa. 31.4.</note> as I take it,<note place="margin">Pſa. 49.15</note> ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as an important note to moue both atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and affection,<note place="margin">Pſa. 68.19</note> and no meruail, for the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in hand is weightie.</p>
            <p>Men haue written much of <hi>Xerxes</hi> fourth comming with his Nauies, <hi>Alexander</hi> with his Armies, and <hi>Salomon</hi> in his royaltie, their fame flewe farre, and their puiſſance was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed, yet were they but men, whoſe breath was in their noſtrels, their power was limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, their arme was but fleſh, their pomp was
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:4533:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>but a flower, ſoone changed into duſt: yea, all was but vanitie and lighter then vanitie it ſelf. But when God commeth foorth, the heauens melted, and the earth ſhooke (ſaith <hi>Dauid</hi>) euen as <hi>Sinay</hi> alſo was moued at the preſence of the God of <hi>Iacob.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 68.8</note> For nowe the Heauens and fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament by violent fraction and rupture of the clowdes ſeemed to burſt in ſunder, and the fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full lightenings and roaring thunderclaps did rend the bending ſides of the ſkie: the darke &amp; wallowing clowdes ſkirmiſhing in the ayre, did driue away with vehement courſe,<note place="margin">Pſa. 77.17</note> as ſhunning moſt fearfully the ſight of this preſence Yea, the ſmothering mount in the rage of the tempeſt, did caſt foorth ſparckling vapours, and flaſhings of fire like another <hi>Aetna</hi> or an image of hell, &amp; thus <hi>God commeth from Teman,</hi> and thus came the holy one from mount <hi>Paran.</hi> Againe, the people ſtricken with aſtoniſhment, ſtoode trembling about the hill, not daring to aproch, but (quaking) crye vnto <hi>Moſes,</hi> Obe thou our ſpokeſman, or elſe we dye. The rattling ſharme of the Trumpe calling on, and ſummoning ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parance, ſeemed to reſemble the daye of doome, when the heauie ſentence (goe ye curſed into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting fire) ſhall be denounced againſt the wicked, Yea,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.4</note> the Sunne was turned into bloud, the foules forſooke the light, the beaſts of the field ſought ſuccour among the dennes of the Lyons, and euery creature elſe that could crall away, ſought a place or corner where to hyde his head, and thus God commeth from <hi>Teman,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:4533:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>and thus came the holie one from mount <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran.</hi> Furthermore, the Lawe it ſelfe (by a <hi>Sub paena</hi>) inforcing a ſtrict and abſolute obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in worke, worde and thought (euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der paine of death,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eu. 28.15</note> and eftſones bewraying the priuation of originall Iuſtice, reuealing ſinne, diſcouering the impuritie of nature, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playing the verie frame of mans heart,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en. 6.5</note> altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of courſe, and out of meaſure wicked. Nowe ſhee hurleth curſes, and nowe ſhee hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth woes. Nowe ſhee poureth out wrath, and nowe ſhee plungeth ſinners: and conſequently dendunceth the heauie ſentence of condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt all fleſh. And thus God commeth from <hi>Teman,</hi> and thus came the holy one from mount <hi>Paran.</hi> The ende and vſe of his thus comming, was to ſtrike the heartes of this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with a reuerend regarde and holye feare of his moſt glorious name and preſence to ſhewe what in iuſtice hee might challenge at ours handes, and the impoſſibilitie on our parte to perfourme it in the leaſt part, thus to bring all men to the knowledge of ſinne, and that thus the Lawe might ſcoole vs vnto Chriſt,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.24</note> where (I praye) doe not miſtake mee to laye theſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putations to the Lawe, as properly the cauſe of ſinne (God forbid.) For, as ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle: the Lawe is pure,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.12</note> the Lawe is holye, and the Lawe is good. But in that ſhee increaſeth ſinne in that ſhee is the myniſter of death, &amp;c. it is <hi>per accidens,</hi> and in our default. For euen as men deformed in their bodies, and blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4533:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>in their faces, while they be compaſſed with darkeneſſe, are not diſcerned from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: but the light once appearing dooth by and by bewraye their ouglineſſe and ſhewe them in their kinde, and yet the cauſe not in the light, but in them ſelues. So the Lawe is our light and glaſſe poincting out our corup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and deformities of nature, and yet the cauſe not in the glaſſe, but in the fleſh, not in the Lawe, but in our nature. And thus you haue heard how God commeth from <hi>Teman,</hi> and the holie one from mount <hi>Paran.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, where <hi>Moſes</hi> calleth the Law <hi>Iugum ferreum,</hi> a hard, a heauie &amp; Iron yoke.<note place="margin">Deur. 28.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Chriſt calleth the Goſpell <hi>Iugum ſuaue,</hi> a ſweete, a light &amp; eaſie yoke.<note place="margin">Mat. 11.3</note> Wher <hi>Eſaie</hi> calleth the Law <hi>Virgam exactoris,</hi> The rod of the oppreſſour.<note place="margin">Eſa. 9.4</note> 
               <hi>Michea</hi> calleth the Goſpel <hi>Virgam paſtoris,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mich. 7.14</note> the rod of the Shepheard, where vnder he guydeth his flock in the paſtures of comfort, and conduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them to the waters of life. Where <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi> tearmeth the Lawe <hi>Mallens diſſipans pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tram,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 23.29</note> The hammer that grindeth the rockes to powder.<note place="margin">Pſa. 45.6</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> calleth the Goſpell <hi>Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trum Regni,</hi> The Scepter of the kingdome, wherewith Chriſt (in all lenitie and mildnes) gouerneth in his Church,<note place="margin">Eſa. 42.3</note> not once breaking the bruſed reed, nor yet quenching the ſmoking flar. Where <hi>S. Paul</hi> calleth the Lawe <hi>Miniſtram mortis,</hi> The miniſter of death. He ſaith,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 3.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the Goſpell is <hi>Miniſtratio vitae,</hi> The adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of life. So that God is nowe come to vs not
<pb facs="tcp:4533:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>from <hi>Teman,</hi> but from heauen: not from mount <hi>Paran,</hi> but from mount <hi>Sion:</hi> not in the ſharme of the trumpe denouncing death,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> but in the ſound of the trumpe proclaiming life: not in the ſhrill voice that cleaueth the mountaines,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Re. 19.11</note> but in the ſtill voyce that cheareth the conſcience. And thus are we come from <hi>Taeman</hi> vnto <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> from <hi>Paran</hi> vnto <hi>Sion,</hi> from a condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning law to a reconciling Goſpell, from a fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Iudge to a mercifull Sauiour: and thus at laſt we are come home from the lande and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Iudaea</hi> to the realme and people of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11.31</note> And nowe will I deale with the laſt cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance, to wit, the ende and vſe of Gods comming in theſe wordes: <hi>The earth is full of his praiſe.</hi> Wherein I will be ſhort, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with an application of the matter of this my tedious diſcourſe to the time and ſtate wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we liue, and ſo will I bequeath you to the Lorde. Where firſt the point I touched in a worde at my entrance (if ye remember) to wit, the excellencie of this worke and mercie of God, towardes the Nation and people of the Iewes, in gining them the Lawe, commeth nowe to a further conſideration, and calleth vs (except we will be like Horſe and Moyle that haue no vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding,<note place="margin">Pſa. 32.9</note> to a more deepe and ſerious medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and examination of the inſpeakable mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the Lord our God towardes our Nation and people of <hi>England,</hi> in vouchſafing vs the Goſpell, and in continuing the ſame now full thirtie yeares expired with diligence preached
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4533:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>in our coaſtes. For this Goſpels ſake bleſſing vs ſtill (by all this ſpace) aboue other Nations with happie peace, a bleſſed Queene, a renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med gouernement, a reuerende myniſterie, a godly maieſtracie, and what not beſides to our good? This Goſpel hath beene the fame and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowme, the defence and glorie,<note place="margin">2. Re. 2.11</note> the chariots and horſemen of <hi>England</hi> to this preſent day &amp; hour. This Goſpell hath poſted through citie &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie without ceaſing to teach and to inſtruct, to correct and to comfort,<note place="margin">2. Ty. 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> to call ſinners vnto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, to gather the diſperſed, to heale the broken hearted,<note place="margin">Eſa. 61.1.2</note> &amp; to preach the acceptable daye of the Lorde. And all this (my brethren) hath beene the time (yea the long and bleſſed time) of our planting, dreſſing and ſpringing,<note place="margin">Eſa. 5.1</note> the Lorde hath long expected (and euen to this houre loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth) to gather and reap the grapes of our vine, the fruites of our figg tree, and the harueſt of our ſo long and pleaſant ſpring.<note place="margin">Luk. 13 6</note> The Lord loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth for the ſheaues of our obedience,<note place="margin">Mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.37</note> repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, faith, mercie, and the feare of his name, with conſcience to walke before him in holines and righteouſnes all the dayes of our life. The end of all is,<note place="margin">Pſa. 76.1</note> that God might be well knowen in <hi>Iudaea,</hi> and that his name might be great in <hi>Iſrael:</hi> that his feare might dwell in our lande, and ſaith my text) that the earth may be full of his praiſe.</p>
            <p>But (alas and thriſe alas therefore) the Lord hath a quarrell (yea a double quarrel) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our lande, the treſpas (yea treſpas vpon
<pb facs="tcp:4533:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>treſpas) is committed in Citie and Countren, and at the corners of each ſtreete, the Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is drawen againſt vs, and the declaration put vpon the file by the Prophet <hi>Hoſeah</hi> (as the Lordes actuarie) in this ſort.<note place="margin">Ho. 4.12</note> There is no trueth, nor mercie, nor knowledge of God in the lande. The euidence followeth and is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by him that will be accuſer, witneſſe and Iudge againſt vs, and this it is: Swearing and lying, killing and ſtealing, and whooring, <hi>Inundauerunt,</hi> haue broken all woonted boundes, and ouerflowed the face of the earth, and what more? <hi>Sanguis ſanguinem tetigit:</hi> Bloud hath touched bloude. One ſinne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendreth another. The cruelties committed in the extreame partes of the lande from the Eaſt and from the Weſt, from the North and from the South, haue met together, min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled themſelues in the bulke and middeſt of the lande, and <hi>Sanguis ſanguinem tetigit.</hi> A gréenous accuſation (you will ſaye) but not fit for this preſence. A fearfull controuerſie of the Lordes, but not well applyed to this people. Well, if you will pardon mee to ſaye as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> did vnto <hi>Theodoſius:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amb. Epiſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9. li. 5</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Neque Imperiale eſt, dicendi libertate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> negare, Neque ſacerdotale quod ſentiat non dicere.</hi> Neither becommeth it the Emperour to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidde free ſpeach: Nor beſeemeth it the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher to forbeare the preſence, I ſhall be content to ouerpaſſe the groſſe enormities whereof the Holye Ghoſt doeth fare the multitude in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:4533:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>the wordes of the Prophet: Which palpable offences be daily whipped out of our ſtreetes, and commonly condemned at open Barre. And I wil come to lurking and lurching ſinnes, euen to treſpas of bloud, not ſo eaſely diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, nor ſo ſeuerely puniſhed, and yet (by your leaue) more accuſtoniably committed, and dailye perpetrated amongeſt vs. For howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer men can waſhe with <hi>Pilate</hi> and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weene to haue cleane handes and cleare hearts from this accuſation of bloud,<note place="margin">Mat. 27.24</note> yet muſt I laye it ſomewhet nearer the conſcience. For it is Gods cauſe, and therefore to be handled indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferently without reſpect of honour or office, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree or dignitie, ſith ſinne is the ſame, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureth of the ſoile, though enbalmed with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes, though clad vpon with veluet or ſattin, or yet cloaked with ſcarlet or purple. Then ſith plaine dealing beſt pleaſeth God and good men, enter I pray into your ſelues, common with your owne hearts and be ſtill. But tell me, tell me, can you be perſwaded there be none among vs that kéepe iudgement from the poore,<note place="margin">Zeph. 33</note> make widdowes their praye,<note place="margin">Eſai. 10.2</note> and the fatherles their ſpoyle?<note place="margin">Exo. 22.22</note> Be there but a fewe (trowe ye) that by vſuries cruell trade deuour the needie,<note place="margin">Exo. 22.25</note> and féede vpon the fleſh of thoſe that fall into their nettes?<note place="margin">Deu. 23.19</note> Be there no oppreſſours of their brethren,<note place="margin">Pro. 28.8</note> that quenche their daily thirſt with the teares of women and children,<note place="margin">Zach. 7.10</note> making breache of bands better than their landes, and grinding the faces of ſuch as are taken in their ſnares?
<pb facs="tcp:4533:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>Be there no carrie tales that giue <hi>Ioabs</hi> ſtabbe with <hi>Iudas</hi> kiſſe,<note place="margin">Leu. 19.16</note> no byting ſlaunderers, that make lying their cuſtome,<note place="margin">Pſal. 15.3</note> and delight to dye their tongues in the bloud of their brethren (as <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> ſpeaketh.<note place="margin">Pro. 26.20</note>) Be there (think you) no ſecrete lurchers that ſtore vp violence in the counting houſe,<note place="margin">Pro. 22.22</note> and robb the poore of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributions for their owne aduantage?<note place="margin">Amos 8.4</note> I praye God the falſe witnes and the ſuborner,<note place="margin">Deu. 19.19</note> the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt queſtman and extorcioner bee not founde with the reſt,<note place="margin">Mich. 3.11</note> in our Counties, and at our Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, in our Cities, and euen at our ſermons. And if they be, God geue them eares to heare, and hearts to repent, in time to iudge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, leſt they be condemned of the Lord: for all theſe be bloudie ſinnes, and all ſuch perſons bloudſuckers, indicted of the blond of Gods people.</p>
            <p>Againe,<note place="margin">Exod. 22 26 27</note> the poore mans pledge wrongfully withholden, the labourers hire kept backe till the morning, the buildings enlarged by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabs</hi> crueltie,<note place="margin">Mat. 26.25</note> the coffers enriched by <hi>Iudas</hi> frecherie, theſe be alſo bloudie ſinnes, and in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of theſe is treſpas of bloud. The ſhops ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with wares, and the warehouſe with ſtore, the tables with dainties, the Cubbords with plate, the Wardrobes with ſutes, and the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries with corne. Take héede (my good bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) leſt in theſe the bloud do alſo cleaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your ſingers. I graunt, before men, deuice may excuſe it, cuſtome will ſmoth it, and (for the time) ſilence can conceale it. But when the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:4533:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lorde ſhall viſite <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> with lanternes, and ſearch your corners with lights,<note place="margin">Zeph. 1.12</note> then bloud will burſt foorth, then bloud will appeare: For there is nothing ſo ſecrete that ſhall not be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.26</note> nor any thing hidden, that ſhall not be knowen. O take heed that many fare not hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for thy ſuperfluitie: that many liue not in penurie for thy prodigalitie: that many go not a begging for thy polling, incroching and inclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: that many ſit not mourning for thy mery making: that manie go not full bare,<note place="margin">Iob. 35.9</note> for thy going ſo braue. For thus, and infinite wayes beſide, thou maiſt become guyltie of bloud. Wo (ſayth <hi>Zephauie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zeph 3.1</note> and wo ſaith <hi>Nahum</hi>) be to the bloudie and robbing citie,<note place="margin">Nah. 3.1</note> the one ſpeaking of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the other of <hi>Niniue,</hi> and why bloudie I praye? ſhee heard not the voice of the poore: the priſoner periſhed in the dungeon, &amp; the begger dyed at the gate for want of reliefe. And therefore, O bloudie Citie, guiltie of their bloud: and why a bloudie Citie? ſhee receiued not correction, faith <hi>Zephonie,</hi> ſhee truſted not in the Lord, ſhee drewe not neare vnto God, &amp; therefore, O bloudie Citie, &amp; O bloudie coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, guiltie of thine owne bloud, and therefore thine owne bloud be vpon thine owne head.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Draco</hi> his lawes were ſaide to be written with bloud, they were ſo forced with cruelties &amp; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie impoſitions. Our lawes of <hi>England,</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be God, are good and renowmed, yet is it to be feared, that for want of due execution, they (ſometime) become like <hi>Solons</hi> cobwebs, and
<pb facs="tcp:4533:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>too often, vnder pretext of iuſtice, hard iniuries be vrged againſt the poore. The Emperour <hi>Titus</hi> who deemed the day loſt, wherein he did not good,) deſired and was inueſted with the dignitie of Prieſthood, to the end to keepe him ſelfe from oppreſſions, from cruelties and ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of bloud. A memorable and right honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable preſident for Iudges, eſperially, and men of authoritie. Yet is it to be feared, wee haue fewe of <hi>Titus</hi> minde at this day in the laud.</p>
            <p>The Iewes made no conſcience to ſhead in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent bloud: they monyed <hi>Iudas</hi> to betray his maſter, ſuch was their crueltie. But when (with a wounded conſcience) he threw it backe vpon them; their money might not come in their treaſurie:<note place="margin">Mat. 27.8</note> no it was the price of bloud: ſuch was their hipocriſie, therfore it came by no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon conſent to buy therewith the field for buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: but by ſpeciall prouidence to diſcerne and name it the bloudie field, or field of bloud euen to this daie.</p>
            <p>Oh my beloued, it is to be feared, wee haue many ſuch fieldes in England. Bloudie fieldes, bloudie vineyardes, bloudie cities, bloudie hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, bloudie Maieſtrates, bloudie Miniſters, bloudie merchants, bloudie Lawyers, bloudie men and bloudie women, bloudie handes and bloudie platters, and the price of bloud within our walles.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ab. 2.11</note> 
               <hi>Lapis de pariete.</hi> (ſayeth our owne Prophet:) a ſtone ſhall crye out of the wall. and the Beame out of the timber ſhall make aunſwere: Woe be to him that buildeth a
<pb facs="tcp:4533:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>towne with bloud, and his houſe with iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. And haue wee not iuſt cauſe, Iudge I praye, to feare that the lande full (not of the praiſe of God) but of curſing and bitterneſſe, of crueltie and bloud. ſhall taſte of fearefull iudgementes for her contempt, and to ſuſpect that the ſinnes of the lande,<note place="margin">Ier. 17.1</note> written with an Iron penne vppon the tables of our heart, and grauen with a Dyamond poynt vppon the hornes Altar, are growen to the qualitie and height of thoſe crying ſinnes, which threaten vs with vtter deſtruction.</p>
            <p>The Lorde of hoaſtes manaced of late to ſtretch the lyne of <hi>Samaria</hi> ouer the Realme of <hi>England,</hi> and to ſound our Cities and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure our families with the Plummet of the houſe of <hi>Ahab,</hi> and not to leaue one to make water againſt a wall. While the daunger was freſh, wee were ſouddeinly daunted, and began to curſe the dayes ſpent in vanitie and wickedneſſe,<note place="margin">Iocl. 1.15</note> which had brought the daye of deſtruction ſo neare vpon our heads. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in our enemies came againſt vs as fierce as the Wolues in the euening, or as the Eagles grée,<note place="margin">Zeph. 33</note> die of their praye, with purpoſe, had not the Lorde in mercie preuented them, to haue taken awaye and trampled vnder féete the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, and to haue erected ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and idolatrie in all our land, to haue bereft vs of our moſt lawfull and louing Soueraigne, the Lordes annoynted Quéene, and to haue turned our inheritance to heatheniſh ſtrangers,
<pb facs="tcp:4533:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>to haue inuaded our countrie with <hi>Edoms</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arme and turned our flouds of peace into chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels of bloud<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to haue murthered the honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble counſail our and graue Iudge, the reuerend Biſhop and venerable maieſtrate,<note place="margin">Deur. 32.25</note> the welthie Citizen and painfull craftſman, the aged ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trone and the chaſte virgine, the infant in the cradle and the cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ple at the gate<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morte or reſpect of ſexe degree or age. And for execution of theſe ſo heauie iudgementes, the Lord threat eneth vs with a people and Nation Idolatrous and vncircumciſed as the <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> extremely cruell and tyrannous as the <hi>Scithi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> at chiuing their exploites not ſo much by martial proweſſe, as by diſhonourable practiſe, not ſo much by courage of their owne, as by cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptng th'aduerſe Captaines, a thing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we haue had tod late experience, of whome I truſt I may ſpeake a troth without ſcandale: And as one ſaid of the <hi>Macedonian</hi> king <hi>Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lips</hi> ſouldiers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Proiuſtie i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, rapinas &amp; caedes pro ſobrie tarmebrie tatem colebant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theopom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Hiſtor.</note> 
               <hi>veritatem &amp; pactorum fidemſuperbe deridebant periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria &amp; impoſturas ducebant laudes ingenii.</hi> Euen ſo ſaye I of theſe, the trouyes of Pupiſts ſouldiers, the Popes vaſſales, whether Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, Frenth; Italian, or whenceſoeuer: if violation &amp; wilful conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt of auncient lawes of Armes, held ſo xſacted, yet amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Heathens, if breach of oathe and promiſe ſealed vpon the conſcience by Sacraments of holy Church: if prophanation of leagues and truce taken ſtill,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4533:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſalued vpon their ſeared conſciences with <hi>Fides non eſt ſeruanda cum Hereticis,</hi> if weapons yet blundred and glutted in the bowels of Gods Saintes, euen then when they déemed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues moſt ſafe vnder the oath and warrant of a King: in a worde, if trecheries and treaſons, maſſacres &amp; murthers, barbarous deſigneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts and gréedie inquiſitions for bloud be apparant teſtimonies of crueltie and infidelitie, then Oh heauens (where now the ſoules are moſt happie in the hand of the Lorde,) and Oh thou earth, where the bodies of ſo many and great ſtates lie now full lowe, murthered by flagitious treche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. O heauen and earth, I ſaye, beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the crueltie and infidelitie of theſe our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies (the ſlaughter-ſlaues of Antichriſt) whome it were eaſie to trace in bloud to appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and ruthfull inſtances of moſt furious tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedies. But (Oh thou bloud thirſtie baude, thus foyled in bloud, and ſtayned with indignities, howſoeuer the Lord ſhall deale with Englande for her tranſgreſſions, for ſurely it is a wicked Nation) yet bloud ſhal be vpon thy head, and bloud in thy hands, bloud vpon thy conſcience, and bloud in barre againſt thee, at the great day when the righteous God ſhall bring ſorrowe vpon thy ſoule in reuenge of his ſeruants bloud poured vpon the face of the earth by thy tiranny. But Oh, how hath the oppreſſor ceaſed and the gold thirſtie <hi>Babell</hi> béene infatuate,<note place="margin">Eſa. 14.4</note> her rodde broken, and the Scepter departed. The Lorde our God hath béene our generall by land, &amp; our
<pb facs="tcp:4533:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>Admyralt by Sea. He that maketh warres to ceaſe in all the worlde, hath knapped the ſpeare in ſunder:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa. 46.9</note> he hath broken the ſhippes of the Sea by the Eaſt winde, and couered our head in the day of battaile, and therefore ſhall euery good man ſing of his praiſe without ceaſing.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa. 30.13</note> O thou King of Nations and hope of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er. 14.8</note> a good God haſt thou béene vnto <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u. 22.17</note> when <hi>Balaam</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> hath curſed, yet haſt thou bleſſed vs. When <hi>Balaac</hi> of <hi>Spaine</hi> hath practiſed miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe againſt vs, then haſt thou diſcouered and diſapointed it.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Sam. 17 3</note> When <hi>Achitophell</hi> at home hath conſpired,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Re. 1.5 &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 17</note> confuſion hath caught him. When <hi>Adoniah</hi> the wilie aſpirer ſought the <hi>Shunamite</hi> to wife and the kingdome withall, the edge of Iuſtice cut him ſhort.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Re. 11 1</note> When <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi> the murthereſſe went about to raze the lyne of the bloud royall, thy prouidence preuented her.<note place="margin">Pſa. 37.15</note> Yea, their ſworde (as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſayeth) hath gone through their owne heart, their gyrdles &amp; garters haue béene their halters, their owne hands their own hangmen, that lay in waite to murther thine annoynted,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 21 17</note> and went about to quench the light in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> This O Lorde was thy doing,<note place="margin">Pſa. 121.5</note> and it was meruailous in our eyes. Thou haſt béen our kéeper vpon our right hand,<note place="margin">Pſa. 118.23</note> the carefull watchman that haſt not forſaken thy <hi>England</hi> in the daye of diſtreſſe: When Prince and people (yea, ſo manye thouſandes that knowe not the right hand from the lefte) were deſigned to a blacke and bloudie daye of deſtruction.<note place="margin">Ionas. 4.11</note> 
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 45.3</note> But the moſt mightie (according to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:4533:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>his worſhippe and renowme) hath gyrt his ſword vpon his thigh, and defended his owne glorie &amp; Goſpell againſt their ſpite,<note place="margin">Pſa. 79 10</note> that would haue ſaide: where is nowe their God? The Lorde hath not withholden his helping hande from his handmaide <hi>Elizabeth</hi> our good &amp; gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Quéene in time of tryall a ſheepe to the ſlaughter: in time of gouernement, a tender Nurſe to the Church, for whoſe ſake he hath heaped ſo many bleſſings vpon our land. The Lorde hath not ſhut his eares at the pitifull moane and crye of ſo manie widdowes and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate Orphanes, whoſe weake and wearie lymmes finde reliefe in our Almeſhouſes and hoſpitalles, ſome monunients of pietie yet left in our land. No, no, howſoeuer it be, a good God is our God, and louing vnto <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 73.1</note> euen to ſuch as be of a pure heart. And therefore it ſhall goe well with the godly: as for our enimies,<note place="margin">Eccl. 8.12</note> he that dwelleth in the Heauens hath laught them to ſcorne: yea, the Lorde ſhall haue them in deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Therefore we will not be afraid, though the earth be moued,<note place="margin">Pſa. 46.2</note> and though the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the hilles be out of courſe. For when the Seas do ſwell and rage horribly, yet the Lorde God is mightier, ſtrong is his hand and mighty is his arme. He hath thruſt his hooke into the iawes of <hi>Sennacherib,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſai. 37.29</note> and the Seas haue ſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the troope of <hi>Pharaos</hi> hoſte. Yea, <hi>Moab</hi> ſhall be our waſhpot,<note place="margin">Exo. 14.27</note> and <hi>Edome</hi> ſhall kneele vnto our ſhooe.<note place="margin">Pſa. 60.8</note> Our footeſteps ſhall be dipped in the bloud of our enimies,<note place="margin">Pſa. 68.23</note> and the tongues of
<pb facs="tcp:4533:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>the dogges ſhall be red with the ſame: So that a man ſhall ſaye, verily there is a rewarde layde vp for the righteous:<note place="margin">Pſa. 38.11</note> doubtles, there is a God that iudgeth the earth. But ſhall we nowe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſecure and caſt away care: ſhall we ſaye, <hi>pax,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er. 8.11</note> 
               <hi>pax,</hi> and all is well, <hi>Non veniet ſuper nos malum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mich. 3.11</note> The <hi>Spanyardes</hi> come no more? Will you ſteale and murther?<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er. 7.9.10</note> commit adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and ſweare falſly, and yet come and ſtande before me (ſaith the Lord) and ſay, we are deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered though we haue committed all theſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominations?<note place="margin">Amos 6.3</note> ſhall we come before the Lorde with bloudie hands and gyltie hearts: put farre off the euill day, and approche to the ſeate of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, and yet thinke to eſcape the iudgements of God? O beloued, take heede is a faire thing, and happie they that be made warefull by the barmes of others: For the maſtife is beaten, that the Lyon might couche: Tis plaine, but a true and patheticall diſtichon:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non vtbs non regio, non aetas vlla ſeueri, Iuditii, exemplis, non domus vlla caret.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No towne, no lande, no age, nor houſe, that time of grace contemnd:</l>
                  <l>But heauie iudgements fell for payt, and wofull was the end.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>When threatenings would not ſerue, nor th'old world could be warned,<note place="margin">Gen. 7.21</note> then came the floode. When dangers were forgotten,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.24</note> and <hi>Sodome</hi> grewe ſecure,<note place="margin">2. Re. 17</note> then came fire from heauen. When <hi>Iſrael</hi> (the mount of the Lords in heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance) waxed wilfull &amp; deſpiſed the Prophets,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:4533:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>then came <hi>Aſshur</hi> the rodde of Gods wrath.<note place="margin">2. Re. 25</note> When <hi>Iuda</hi> (the ſignet of the Lords right hand) became indurate, and would not be reclaymed, then came <hi>Nabucadneſſar</hi> with fire and ſword. When <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſored with the Egle,<note place="margin">Lam. 1.1</note> &amp; made her neſt among the ſtarres, Oh ſudden was her downfall to ſorrowe and deſolation. When the <hi>Brittaines</hi> would be wantons &amp; derided <hi>Gildas</hi> warnings, then came the <hi>Romanes,</hi> and then came their woe: For <hi>Propter auaritiam &amp; ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinam principum, propter iniquitatem &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtitiam Iudicum, propter deſidiam &amp; diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium Epiſcoporum, propter luxuriam &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietatem populi, patriam perdiderunt Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanni.</hi> Will you know what rooted out the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Brittaines</hi> out of this land, and brought a moſt lamentable face of a comon wealth vpon the ſame? It was the couetouſnes and oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Nobles, and Peeres, the iniuries &amp; extortions of the Iudges and Lawyers, the ſlouth and diſſention among the Biſhops &amp; cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, the rowte and riot of the people and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. Theſe, theſe (my brethren) be the ſinnes that bring kingdomes to ruyne, and populous cities to deſolate heapes of ſtones, and God is chiefe Iuſtice that ſtriketh Nations with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,<note place="margin">Pſa. 107.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and powreth contempt vpon Princes for their diſobedience. He hath his Angels a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, and his armies belowe with a ſtorehouſe of plagues to diſcharge vpon the wicked.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 11.6</note> He can let fall a bloudie ſword vpon the rebellious Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. He can pine a pampered people with penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb facs="tcp:4533:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſcant. He can ſtrip the land of pride to a hiſſing and ſhame.<note place="margin">Hoſ. 2.3</note> He can ſmite with the peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence after the manner of Egypt.<note place="margin">Pſ. 7.12.13</note> Surely his howe is full bent, and his ſworde readie whet. He is comming to execution with the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of death. O, it is full time then for vs to turne vnto the Lorde,<note place="margin">Zeph. 2.1.2</note> to ſowe in teares that we might reape in ioy,<note place="margin">Amos. 8.10</note> to ſéeke the Lorde while he may be found, and to gather our ſelues before the decrée come foorth, to turne our feaſtes into faſtes, and our ſongs into ſighings, to gyrd ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe about our loynes, and to rend our hearts with mourning: yea, the time is come for prince and ſubiects (with the King and people of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niue</hi>) to come foorth in ſackcloth and aſhes,<note place="margin">Ionas. 3.6</note> for the Bride (with Quéene <hi>Heſter</hi> to forſake her cloſet,<note place="margin">Heſt. 4.15</note> and the Bridegrome his chamber, For the miniſter of the Lorde to crye betwéene the porche and the Altar,<note place="margin">Iocl. 2.16 17</note>) ſpare Oh Lorde, ſpare thine heritage, that we all come forth in mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning cheare with the teares of repentance, to turne away Gods heauie wrath and prepared deſtruction. For his hand is not ſhortened, but that he can paye vs home, nor his wrath (for all this) ſo withdrawen, but that he will reuenge. Againe, our caſe is not ſo deſperate, nor wee ſo farre falne from God. Our wickednes is not of that height, nor our ſinnes of ſo déepe die, but vnfained repentance will reconcile vs vnto God, and blot out all remembrance of former diſpleaſure out of his ſight. If therfore there be any conſolation in Chriſt Ieſus,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hil. 2.1</note> any deſire or
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:4533:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>liking of Chriſtian religion. If there be any loue or loyaltie towardes her ſacred maieſtie, or care in thy heart of thy natiue countrie. If any hope of reſurrection to eternall life, anye lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging or looking for the kingdome to come: Let thy repentance, thy teares, thy ſorrowe for ſinne, thy couenant to ſerue the Lord vnderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken this day, &amp; (in ſome good meaſure of grace) performed all the daies of thy life, be meanes to ſue for thy pardon, to reconcile thee to the Lord, to turne away his wrathfull indignation, and to continue his wonted mercies towarde the realme of <hi>England.</hi> And here let euery one be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with himſelfe, and ſéeke firſt a reformation in his owne conſcience. And herein God helpe vs and proſper the worke of our hands vpon vs O Lorde, proſper thou our handie worke:<note place="margin">Pſa. 90.17</note> So <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſhalbe builded,<note place="margin">Pſa. 79.13</note> and thy <hi>Zion</hi> neuer be remoued, but ſtand faſt for euer. So we that be thy people and ſhéepe of thy paſture, ſhall giue thée thanks for euer. So ſhall our victory be thy glorie: the fall of our foes, the aduauncement of thy Goſpel: the preſeruation of our liues, the amendment of our wicked liues hereafter, that in life and death we may be thine, and glorifie thée our rocke, our defence, &amp; only God of truſt, euen all the dayes of our life. That after our ſhort and vncertaine courſe here belowe ſpent in thy ſeruice and feare: wée may at laſt depart in peace from this vale of miſerie to thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of glorie, there to raigne with thée for euer, and to be ſatiate with the fulneſſe of thy glorie
<pb facs="tcp:4533:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>in the heauens for euermore, and that by thy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone merite, and in the only mediation of Ieſus Chriſt our ſole ſufficient Saniour, to whome O Father of lightes, together with thee and the Holy Ghoſt, three diſtinct in perſon, one onlye true, eternall, and euerliuing God be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall praiſe, glorie, power, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, and maieſtie, both now and for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>LONDON <hi>Printed by Iohn Wolfe for</hi> Edward Aggas. 1589.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4533:29"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
